If today, out of all days, you
told yourself this morning:
"Man, what a perfect day
for cybersecurity", then...
Then it doesn't even matter, because you
did not say that. Nobody talks like that.
But, if at some point you just
decided one day that you want to
learn some cybersecurity, that is awesome!
That is perfect, because I'm going to share
with you the most complete series of tutorials
on this topic that you will ever find, and,
as a nice bonus, I will also prepare you to
pass the CompTIA CySA+ certification exam.
Why does this training exist? Well, I made
this training because I was just a bit
disappointed by the current content that's out
there and I wanted to make something better.
Actually, I wanted to make something much
better than what you can currently buy from
big name training companies.
And also, why cybersecurity?
Well, first of all because I personally love
it, and secondly, because it's an awesome
topic and it's useful for pretty much anyone,
nowadays, who uses a computer or a smartphone,
so yeah... basically to anyone, and we are
going to need cybersecurity right until,
I don't know... forever.
It's always going to be relevant
because it's everywhere, it's in a non-stop
process of change, it's constantly adapting,
so if you like cybersecurity, and you're
even thinking about doing it for a living,
your job will always be safe.
Well, at least as long as you keep up to date.
Another reason is that cybersecurity is supposed
to be fun because it's a never-ending strategy
game that everybody is playing.
The good guys are playing it,
the bad guys are playing it, the guys you entrust
your money in a bank, or when you go shopping,
the guys that hold your email, and cat videos, and
TikToks, the guys who make water, light, and...
pizza... right, to reach your house, and even
those guys with the tanks, rockets, and drones.
So, this game should keep you up at night
because it's everywhere. it's about your
life, and you should be passionate about it.
Hi, my name is Andrew and I will lead you
through this awesome quest on cybersecurity,
and, if you want, also for the CompTIA CySA+ exam.
So, who is this Andrew guy and why does he think
that he can teach me something?
Well, let me give you two reasons:
First of all, my origin story says that I've
been working in IT for more than 10 years,
and I keep saying more than 10, because the real
number kind of makes me feel old, but I also hold
this many technical certifications, and I will
not go over all of these, but have a look over my
Linkedin profile, in the description and add me if
you want, but suffice to say that I do have some
experience with networking, security, and DevOps.
And, yes, my dear relatives and friends, I am able
to fix your computers, and routers, and printers.
Now, second reason, have a look over the videos
in my channel and decide for yourself
if I know what I'm talking about.
But, if I do, please subscribe and help this
channel grow, because I really need your support
as all this content is always going
to be free. Free as in free beer,
not any other sneaky type of free.
So what's in it for you? I will share with you
everything that you need to pass the CompTIA CySA+
exam and I will also share from my experience,
and from all my previous certification exams,
because I realized one day, after I went through
so many certifications, and aspects of IT, that
I've ended up with a very nice perspective of all
these topics and I wanted to share that with you.
I want to share which things matter and
which things don't, which concepts
apply only in books and trainings,
and which concepts will make people laugh at
you if you want to apply them in real life.
And for free! There won't be any paywall,
no pay-per-view, no demo videos that
send you to buy the rest.
Everything will be here, and free,
as long as Youtube shall live.
Don't trust me yet? Subscribe now
and let's see in 10 years who was right.
So, how are we going to do this? Well,
we're going to follow the exam objectives, the
official exam blueprint, because this gives us
a very nice structure to build our content.
You should check out the CompTIA website,
download the exam blueprint, but be
aware that I will slightly change the
order of some topics simply because, in my
brain, they make a lot more sense that way.
So go have a look over the official page of the
CySA+ exam. That's some very useful information,
like: the skills that you will learn, some
jobs that match this certification, and some
exam details like how many questions you'll get,
what's the passing score, and stuff like that.
Now, for a detailed list of exam topics, you
just need to fill in a form to download the PDF,
which, fortunately, I have right here.
So, we have five domains, or major topics
to cover. We'll talk about threats and
vulnerabilities, and how to make some
sense of these in a more structured manner.
We'll talk about the day-to-day life of someone
working in security operations. We'll talk about
describing threats, measuring them to know just
how badly you could be, or have been hacked
in the past, how not to freak out if you find
vulnerabilities in your systems, and how to find
them, some tools that will help you with scanning
and assessments, some specific threats for things
that don't exactly look like a computer, you know,
like mobile devices, industrial systems,
your PlayStation, Internet of Threats
Uh, sorry... Internet of Things, devices,
you know, like smart refrigerators,
and smart home devices.
Moving on to the cloud,
because it does have its own set of threats,
even though we like to think about the cloud
as being something that just works. An entire huge
section about types of attacks, and trust me this
is going to be huge, but also very insightful.
Then we'll move on to software and systems like
servers and workstations, and this is also where
we'll talk about virtualization and containers,
software development and best practices, or
how not to develop some piece of code that
shoots us in the foot. That's secure coding.
Securing low-level hardware against some really
nasty and hard to detect attacks
Working with specialized devices
like firewalls and IPSs, and quite a few others.
About being proactive and looking for threats
even when you don't have any proof
that you've been compromised yet.
Good luck explaining those
work hours to your boss!
Some newer concepts here about automation,
because, well, you know the saying:
"If it's worth doing once, it's worth automating"
Moving on to incident response, which is how not
to panic when something bad really happens, how
to minimize damage and save as much money and as
many butts in a compromised company as possible.
Learn how to investigate and understand what
happened if a cyber crime was committed.
When the boss comes to you to
ask "What's happening here?
Are we under attack?", and you go "Whaaaat?!".
And, going a bit deeper and really
investigate, you know, like CSI style,
in order to, well, if you took a beating at
least learn to defend yourself the next time.
Fool me once, shame on you.
Fool me twice, shame on me.
At least assuming the same type of foolery.
And, the boring part.
Nah, just kidding! It's not boring,
it's about policies, compliance,
and IT governance, and regulations, and,
Nah, I'm kidding, it is
boring! But it's on the exam.
About trying to look smart, while predicting
the future like you have some proof,
when everybody knows that you don't,
also known as "Evaluating risk".
Then, documenting your previous attempt at
looking smart. That is: Risk Assessments.
And, finally, you should
be ready to pass the exam.
Now you might think: "That. is. a lot!"
"What did I sign up for?"
Well, it's a lot because security
has never been more complex.
There's just so much diversity in
everything that's IT around us.
Just a little while ago you only
had to secure, perhaps, your
router, or a firewall, so that hackers
would not mess around with your website.
But today, we have so many devices interconnected
from wearables, phones, smart kitchen appliances,
robot vacuum cleaners, which sold like crazy
during this pandemic, smart light bulbs,
smart cars, smart windows, smart i don't
know, vibrators, and whatever scary smart
things might be out there.
And this is the new internet.
It's also the new playground for hackers.
Attacks evolved too.
We hear in the media about
ransomware, APTs, and many, many more.
We also work from home a
lot now, and you might say
"Yeah, but we have VPNs, and that's the
definition of security right there!".
Yeah, but who might have access to your laptop?
What other infected devices you might have in
your home, without you even knowing about them?
Because, let's be honest, who has
enterprise grade security at home?
And even large enterprises get hacked,
and, by the way, are you even at home,
or relaxing on some beach, in a mountain
cabin, in some hotel, in your parents home,
on a wireless network that's so insecure that
you shouldn't even watch cat videos on it.
So if you're wondering if this exam
is right for you, or what exactly you
should know before starting to study, I would
say the requirements are not very high, but
you will need some basic computer knowledge
and networking concepts, before you start.
But, I would guess that you're
probably not attempting the CySA+ exam
if this morning was the first time
you ever started the computer.
But, for more details on exactly how difficult
is the exam, and what you should expect,
keep watching, because this is exactly what
we'll be talking about in the next video.
So please subscribe, and see you next time
you