I know you just want to start learning
right now, but, before we begin,
it's very important to set the right expectations
I'm going to tell you exactly just how difficult
should you expect the CompTIA CySA+ exam to be
Trust me, you're going to need this
Hi, I'm Andrew, this is Certify Breakfast,
and I'm about to tell you exactly how
hard this exam is going to kick your butt
So, I'm going to give you 10 pieces
of advice, which I strongly believe
that you should know before the exam.
Most certifications tell you that you need
this much experience to ride in their exam roller
coaster, and while the CySA+ also does this, here
Even though it's not a mandatory requirement, I
would so much want to tell you that you don't need
this much experience, and I am going to tell you
that you do not need that on the job experience
It's nice to have it, will make
your life easier on exam day,
but don't give up just because
you don't have that job experience
You can learn everything
you need to know right now
The CySA+ exam expects you
to have two major skills
The first one is about understanding basic
security principles that apply in computer
networks, and the second one is about you
being able to understand and interpret the
outputs and commands from some
of those specific security tools
Which means great news for you, right? Exam
study can be done in the comfort of your pajamas,
and also becoming familiar with
these tools can also be done in a
couch potato mode, from the comfort of
your home as we'll see on number three
Security without tools is just a bunch
of policies, and we already have our dear
CISSP exam for that, so the CySA+ exam
wants you to know how to use certain
tools and how to read some text outputs or
to understand some graphical user interface
It's not so difficult as it sounds: your
laptop is more than enough for these tools
Most of them are free anyway and come
packed in the Kali Linux distribution
and you certainly don't need to buy
any additional hardware for your labs
And if you're a bit lazy you can even get
away with just watching these tools in action,
like in our next videos
And even though the exam will test just how
comfortable you are around security devices,
such as firewalls, IPSs, you don't need to have
those in your home or at work, right, obviously
Which brings us to security vendors
CompTIA exams pride themselves for being
vendor neutral or vendor agnostic so they
don't focus on a specific vendor out there
Well, the problem is the real world IS vendor
specific, obviously, so getting some experience
from real firewalls, antivirus solutions,
I don't know... spam filters, means
that you get vendor specific experience
Well, the good news is that CySA+ exam
tries to stay away from specific solutions,
so as long as you can read any type of firewall
rule, or any type of Syslog entry, you'll be fine
It doesn't matter if you've only
seen Cisco, or Check Point, or
Dell before. Even if you haven't
seen any, just keep watching
and also number five
I've been through more than 30
certification exams and I've never,
ever, found one single source of information
that helps you get that 100 in the exam
I love the trainings from sites like
LinkedIn or Pluralsight, but, unfortunately,
those videos barely scratch the surface of
what you need to know to pass this CySA+ exam
So, if you learn from other CySA+
trainings out there, I beg you
don't make the mistake of assuming
that it's going to be enough
That kind of overconfidence is a
recipe for disaster on the exam day,
so I strongly suggest that
you do your own research
Google is your friend, exploit
it, you know, not in a bad way
One thing I don't like is ambiguous, and
non-technical questions in a technical exam
Questions that ask you about the best
solution without telling you it should
be the most secure one, the cheapest one,
the most convenient one for the users
Questions that ask you about trends, and
opinions, that don't give you enough context
From my perspective a technical
question should be like a computer:
give me the right input the question and I will
give you the right and the only right answer
After three CompTIA certifications, so far, I
must say that they do have this habit of pushing
these weird, ambiguous questions in their exams,
very often, worse than other vendors out
there and, yes, Cisco, I'm looking at you!
You're pushing marketing in your
exams and I don't know which is worse
Don't worry you, will begin to
understand the mindset of the test maker
We'll make some dedicated videos on
practice tests to help you understand
how CompTIA thinks, and then it hits
you with something like number seven
Out-of-date questions are
about technologies that are
rarely used nowadays but for some reason
someone forgot them in the exam pool
Things like mitigating some attack which hasn't
been an issue since, I don't know, 10 years ago
Or assuming that antivirus software
hasn't evolved in the past 20 years
Talking about BlackBerry phones
in the enterprise, stuff like that
Make sure you subscribe, as we will cover
these as well, at least in one special video
Which brings us to another
surprise in the exam, number eight
If you're facing the CySA+ exam after going
through the Network+ and Security+ exams,
like I did, you're in for a bit of
a surprise, which kicks in about
after the first 15 minutes of the
exam: it's a bit more difficult
I must admit, I kind of breezed through
the Network+ and the Security+ exams
They had a lot of weird questions, but they
were not as difficult as the CySA+ exam,
which really goes in depth on some topics, and
expects you to pay a lot of attention to details
Many questions will punish you
for not paying enough attention to the
context, or for reading an output in a hurry
Don't make that mistake! Don't rush!
And, I'm not saying it's a bad
thing, because in real life,
as well, the devil is in the details, right?
Just pay attention and you should be fine
I've studied for the CISSP, Security+, CySA+,
Certified Ethical Hacker and the CCNA
CyberOps exams, all of them about security
There's a lot of overlap in these
topics, a lot of the content is the same,
a lot of the questions are going to be similar,
so, if you've been through some of these you
might find that the CySA+ exam is a bit easier,
right, than most people are going to find it
Does that mean that some of these are
redundant as certifications? Well,
perhaps, but, in my opinion,
it's a good thing because
it helps you really refresh that information
in your brain and store it on the long term
And, one more thing if you Google
search for CompTIA CySA+ exam questions,
you will probably find some
results, some PDFs some forums
And you're probably thinking:
"Now he's going to tell us not to search
for those, because it's not ethical"
And yes, I'm going to tell you it's not
ethical, but here's a better reason:
First, the answers to those questions
are painfully wrong and mislead you,
and secondly, they give you a very bad
sense of security, because very often
you will realize that the exam has nothing to
do with these questions that you found online
and that's a very bad thing to realize
on the first five minutes of the exam
All right! So, enough beating around the bush
Let's get down to business and jump
into the first topic of the first domain
for the CySA+ certification exam
and don't forget to subscribe,
if you want to do a good deed for today and you
want to encourage free IT certification training