Well, you're probably learning
this stuff, firstly, because
it's exciting to learn something new
we'll see how many of you stick to the end
and secondly, because your current job, or
your future job requires you to know the stuff,
or even your past job, in case you were
kicked out for messing up something terribly
So, let's see what a security
analyst does after the morning coffee
The job titles in this cybersecurity
business and, more precisely, the titles
you might be able to put on your résumé, with a
certification like CySA+ include lots of jobs like
Security Analyst or Cybersecurity
Analyst, Security Consultant,
CSO - that's Chief Security Officer, Security
Engineer, even just a Network Engineer or
Consultant - those guys are expected to
have their security knowledge up to date
also Server Admins, Database
Admins, and even Developers
Now, we'll cover aspects that
apply to all these jobs and more
and, you can even add the word "Cloud"
before each and every of these titles,
because most of these traditionally on-premises
jobs now apply to cloud environments as well
So, for the sake of consistency let's just
refer to one, that's the Cybersecurity Analyst
Well, first things first: what is cybersecurity?
Cybersecurity refers to the protection of
any information that belongs to you, or to the
company, from unauthorized access, attacks, theft,
data damage over computer systems and networks,
so, at the end of the day, it's everything
that you are doing to protect your digital data
Now coming back here to the role
of the Cybersecurity Analyst,
why is that guy getting paid?
Well, a Cybersecurity Analyst is a senior
position within an organization security team
with direct responsibility for
protecting sensitive information,
and preventing unauthorized access to
electronic data, and the systems that process it
So, the analyst can also have juniors under
his or her wing, and usually reports to the
CISO, so the boss is going to be the
Chief Information Security Officer
But, what exactly do they do all day?
Well, implementing, and configuring
security controls such as
firewalls, intrusion detection systems, and
other threat management appliances and software
They work in a leading role in the
computer security incident response team or
CSIRT or security operations center
(SOC) to manage security incidents,
auditing security processes and procedures,
performing due diligence on third parties,
and delivering employee training, performing
risk assessments, vulnerability assessments
and penetration tests, and recommending
appropriate security controls or procedures
And, they also have to keep
themselves informed and up-to-date,
so that they can provide threat intelligence
awareness and advice on legal compliance,
regulatory issues, not just the technical ones,
And well, as far as the job requirements go,
it is kind of expected for you to have an
up-to-date technological knowledge, creative
thinking, problem-solving skills, and even empathy
You have to think sometimes like a hacker,
think like someone who does
harm, or seeks some personal gain
Some non-technical language
skills are also very useful,
you should be a very detail-oriented person, and
when bad things happen calm and self-controlled
In many organizations Cybersecurity Analysts are
likely to work as part of a
security operations center or an SOC
An SOC is a location where security professionals
monitor and protect critical information assets in
an organization and, well, because SOCs can be
difficult to establish, maintain, and finance,
they are usually employed by larger corporations
like a government agency or a healthcare company
that deals in personally identifiable
information and other companies like that
SOCs, despite their differences in
size, scope, and responsibility,
tend to be designed with a
few key principles in mind
So, an SOC should be first of all
supported by organizational policies,
giving it the authority it needs to be effective
It should be able to balance its size
and its presence in the organization
without overstepping its bounds
It should be staffed with motivated people
I'll tell you a secret here: this is
one job where if you're lucky and lazy
enough you might not have to lift
a finger and get away with it
Unless shit hits the fan,
definitely don't do that!
But, beware that unmotivated individuals
can be very harmful for your organization,
especially if they're in charge of your defense
Think about going to war with an
unmotivated army, or a football match,
where players in the team
have no motivation to win
This is bad, right?
It should be staffed with skilled professionals,
and not overstaffed with unqualified personnel
It should be able to incorporate a wide variety of
security processes into a single operation center
It should be equipped to
perform incident response duties
It should be able to protect the SOC's own
systems and infrastructure from attacks
Be aware of the strengths and the
limitations of each tool that it uses
And, it should be aware of the
nuances involved in monitoring
to be able to separate the signal from the noise
we'll talk more about this in future lectures
And, of course it should be willing to
collaborate with other SOCs to share
valuable information on threat
intelligence and mitigation techniques
All right, so for the exam make sure
you understand the responsibilities
of a Cybersecurity Analyst
it's also equally important to understand
which tasks DO NOT fall under the
responsibility of a Cybersecurity Analyst
and you should be able to identify the main
functions of a security operation center
Thanks for watching, don't forget to
subscribe, and see you on the next video